# Adrián Cruz Ramos

Email: adriancrz93@gmail.com | Location: San Antonio, TX 78203 | Phone: (210) 636-1067

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/adrian-cruz-ramos/

### **SUMMARY**

Project Manager with experience as an IoT entrepreneur and educated in engineering, product development, and business commercialization. I successfully landed the first major client and delivered a fully functional MVP of a San Antonio based startup focused on hassle-free client management solutions and provisionally patented an infant monitoring device capable of analyzing vital signs in real-time and providing relevant feedback for parents.

## **EXPERIENCE**

**Independent Rough Terrain Center** (formerly known as Kalmar RT Center), San Antonio, TX

2017 - Present

Rough terrain mobile equipment solutions for the military, fracking and commercial industries.

**Quality Engineer Manager** – <u>Previously: Supplier Development Engineer (2017), Sr. Quality Supervisor (Early 2018)</u>

- Managed a Supply Chain of over 60 suppliers to ramp up their manufacturing processes and deliver conforming prototypes.
- Accomplished to reduce the number of annual defects detected from almost 5,000 units to less than 800 a year.
- Streamlined suppliers manufacturing process to reduce their annual Parts Per Million values from an average of 20K to 3k.
- Lead the company's Continuous Improvement Program and achieved cumulative savings of approximately \$100,000/year.
- Implemented an Internal Audit Program which enabled departments to increase their output productivity by 30%.
- Successfully handled the company's ISO 9001:2008 recertification as well as transitioning to the ISO 9001:2015 certification.
- Reduced the total amount of customers Product Quality Deficiency Reports by 60%.
- Improved On-Time Delivery rate from 50% to a steady 95% by developing a more practical order fulfilling process.
- Developed a FIFO hose racking system for the Warehouse that reduced the amount of non-conforming shelf-life customer complaints by 100%, improved stock control, and saves the company a total of \$35,000/year.
- Created a comprehensive directory which detailed the company's strategy and approach to reduce and prevent potential corrosion failures supporting the company's winning bid for a \$63M government contract.
- Increased the department's efficiency and efficacy for processing prototype parts with a rejection rate less than 5%.

**Elop LLC,** Austin, TX **2017 – 2019** 

Automated native mobile app development.

# **Co-Founder & Technical Sales Lead**

- Semifinalist on PitchTexas 2018 competition Best-in-class student-led startups from across the US compete live on stage at SXSW for a chance to win \$35K from a panel of entrepreneurial judges and venture capitalists.
- Fourth runner up on Texas TVL Start-Up 2018 Competition Startup competition that allows Graduate University of Texas students to pitch their ideas to a panel formed by Austin's tech community for a chance of winning a \$15K cash prize.
- Developed a comprehensive business-to-business plan by performing a thorough market validation analysis on automated mobile app development companies, interviewed stakeholders on several Fortune 100 companies and gathered requirements as well as details on their current problems, analyzed budgets access from stakeholders, and layed out the framework for the sales strategy.
- Introduced the first beta user into the system to fully develop their app prototype.
- Built the startups landing page using reactJS libraries the website consisted of an about, services, team, and contact pages.

### Checkups LLC, San Antonio, TX

2016 - 2017

Mobile and web platform for client location tracking, data management, and compliance verification.

## **Business Development Lead**

- Conducted a market competitive analysis and benchmarking to identify the organization's strengths and build viable launch business model and marketing strategy.
- Deployed direct marketing and branding campaign through different Bail Bond trade shows and annual meetings; build brand awareness by implementing targeted promotions and establishing partnerships with key players among the Professional Bondsmen of Texas.
- Performed sales activities from cold calling to customer support; acquired and managed company's first five client accounts, including Checkups currently largest client totaling a revenue of \$30K/year.

- Collaborated on Checkups new product line for Bexar county trails court managed both front and back end developments through agile frameworks.
- Inducted Bexar trails court as first county client with a deal for \$5 per user; secured an approximate revenue of \$80K/year.

## **BabyButton,** Austin, TX **2015 – 2017**

Smart monitoring device with data analytics for newborns.

#### Founder

- Build and design an infant monitoring device with a machine learning suite capable of sensing and analyzing sleeping positions, heart rate, calculate blood oxygen levels, and display the information on a mobile device via Bluetooth.
- Conducted an extensive market validation phase interviewing more than 20 professionals, surveyed over 100+ parents, and organized 5 different focus groups.
- Received a provisional patent for a "forehead reflectance based pulse oximeter monitor".
- Built a basic android application using C and C++ on the Android Native Development Kit the app allowed the end-user to retrieve real-time data from the smart sensor and review the data analysis given.
- Second runner up on UTSA \$100K CITE 2016 competition Student Technology Venture Competition to give students hands-on experience as early stage entrepreneurs.
- Fourth runner up on TVL Start-Up 2017 competition.
- Semifinalist on PitchTexas 2017 competition.

### **PROJECTS**

## DoggoCalendar | https://doggocalendar.herokuapp.com/

Dog play date scheduler - this website helps dog owners to schedule dog play dates with their fellow dog owner friends.

- Role: Project Manager, Lead Developer & Designer
- Management techniques/frameworks: SCRUM

### **FIFO Hose Racking System**

Improved warehouse lot control, traceability of shelf-life requirements, and customer fulfillment for all hydraulic hoses stock/orders.

- Role: Project Manager
- Management techniques: Lean Six Sigma

### **EDUCATION**

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN, Center for Professional Education, Austin, TX

May 2020

Full Stack Development Bootcamp Certificate

SCRUM ALLIANCE March 2020

<u>Certified Scrum Master</u>

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, Extended Education, San Antonio, TX

December 2019

Lean Six Sigma Green Belt Certification

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN, McCombs School of Business, Austin, TX

May 2018

Master of Science in Technology Commercialization (MSTC)

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, College of Engineering, San Antonio, TX May 2016

## **Bachelor of Science in Biomedical Engineering**

• GPA: 3.67 - Cum Laude

### **ADDITIONAL**

- **Current member of**: The National Society of Leadership and Success, PHI KAPPA PHI Honors Society, TAU BETA PI The Engineering Honors Society: Texas MU Chapter, Admissions Ambassador of the MSTC Program.
- Microsoft Office: Word, PowerPoint, Projects
- **Tech Skills:** HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Materialize, MongoDB, MySQL, CRUD data persistence, Git, Github, RESTful APIs, ReactJS
- Languages: Spanish (Native); English (Fluent); French (Fluent); German (Intermediate); Italian (Intermediate)
- Social Service: Voluntary work on STEM programs for elementary and high schools in San Antonio.
- Work Eligibility: Eligible to work in the United States under USMCA (NAFTA), OPT, and/or sponsorship visa (H1-B)